<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<vst:Guide xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2001/xaml/presentation"
           xmlns:vst="clr-namespace:Microsoft.VisualStudio.Guide;assembly=Microsoft.VisualStudio.Shell.UI.Internal"
           Title="Personalizing your environment"
           Description="Make Visual Studio yours through these flexible and inclusive tools."
           Id="IdeCustomization"
           SortOrder="50"
           EstimatedMinutesToComplete="8"
           IconPath="Customize_Guide.png">
    <vst:Step Title="Welcome to the VS IDE customization guide!"
              Id="Intro">
        <vst:Step.Description>
            <![CDATA[
In this guide, you'll learn to:
- Select a profile for settings
- Change your Visual Studio theme
- Configure other settings
- Back up settings
- Sync and sharing settings
- Customize toolbars

Select **Continue** to proceed.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Select a profile"
              Id="SelectProfile"
              MenuToHighlight="Tools">
        <vst:Step.Description>
            <![CDATA[
After you installed Visual Studio, you might have seen a dialog asking you to choose a profile (such as General, C#, or Web Development).
This applies a curated collection of settings, including a default window layout and key bindings. If you were signed in and have used VS in the past, we skipped that dialog and applied the profile you used last time.  

To change your profile:
1. Select **Tools** > [**Import and Export Settings...**](vscmd://Tools.ImportandExportSettings)
1. Select **Reset all settings** and click **Next**.
1. If you have customizations you want to preserve, select **Yes, save my current settings**; otherwise, select **No, just reset settings, overwriting my current settings**.  Click **Next**.
1. Select the profile you want to apply and click **Finish**.
1. Select **Close** to exit the dialog.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Change the color theme"
              Id="ChangeTheme"
              MenuToHighlight="Tools">
        <vst:Step.Description>
            <![CDATA[
By default, Visual Studio uses the Dark theme. Your theme will sync across machines and Visual Studio instances when you're signed in. To change your theme, select an item under **Tools** > **Theme**.

To install more themes, select **Tools** > **Theme** > [**Get More Themes**](vscmd://Tools.GetMoreThemes).

When you change your theme, any customizations you've made under **Tools** > **Options** > **Environment** > [**Fonts and Colors**](vscmd://Tools.Options?args=57F6B7D2-1436-11D1-883C-0000F87579D2)
are backed up, so if you switch back to the previous theme they'll be restored.
]]>

        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Configure other settings"
              Id="OtherSettings">
        <vst:Step.Description>
          <![CDATA[
Most Visual Studio settings can be found under **Tools** > [**Options**](vscmd://Tools.Options). Alternatively, you can use [global search](vscmd://Window.QuickLaunch)
{KeyboardShortcut:Window.QuickLaunch} to find settings in the Options dialog.  

For example, this setting changes the Tab key to add spaces instead of tab characters in plain text files:
1. Select **Tools** > [**Options**](vscmd://Tools.Options).
1. In the tree view (left side), expand **Text Editor** > **Plain Text** and select on **Tabs**.
1. In the settings view (right side), select **Insert spaces**.
1. Select **OK**.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Back up settings"
              Id="BackUp">
        <vst:Step.Description>
          <![CDATA[
You can capture your current IDE settings in an export file. This may be useful to share with others or restore later in a new install. 

To capture your current IDE settings in an export file:
1. Select **Tools** > [**Import and Export Settings...**](vscmd://Tools.ImportandExportSettings)
1. Select **Export selected environment settings** and click **Next**.
1. Select the settings you want to save and click **Next**.
1. Edit the file name and directory, or accept the defaults, and click **Finish**.
1. Click **Close** to exit the dialog.

To restore IDE settings from a file:
1. Select **Tools** > [**Import and Export Settings...**](vscmd://Tools.ImportandExportSettings)
1. Select **Import selected environment settings** and click **Next**.
1. If you have customizations you want to preserve, select **Yes, save my current settings**; otherwise, select **No, just import new settings, overwriting my current settings**. Click **Next**.
1. Select the file you want to import and click **Next**. Use the **Browse...** button to select a file that's not in the list.
1. Select the profile you want to apply and click **Finish**.
1. Select **Close** to exit the dialog.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Configure roaming and sharing"
              Id="RoamingAndSharing">
        <vst:Step.Description>
          <![CDATA[
By default, Visual Studio syncs some settings to the cloud if you're signed into Visual Studio. These include most settings under **Environment** and **Text Editor** in **Tools** > **Options**.
A few settings, such as your recently used projects and solutions, are shared across installs on the same machine, but not synced in the cloud.

To disable this syncing behavior:
1. Select **Environment** > [**Accounts**](vscmd://Tools.Options?args=FCA0A84C-0C77-43DE-B026-65B8C9F57485) in **Tools** > [**Options**](vscmd://Tools.Options)
1. Uncheck **Synchronize settings across devices and installs on this machine (enabling this may overwrite local settings)** and click **OK**

This will leave your current settings unchanged, and subsequent customizations will affect only this Visual Studio install.
If you choose to re-enable roaming and sharing later, your local customizations will be overwritten by any shared settings, just like they are when you sign in to VS.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>
    <vst:Step Title="Select toolbars"
              Id="Toolbars">
        <vst:Step.Description>
            <![CDATA[
By default, VS shows a standard toolbar at all times and adds other toolbars dynamically depending on the scenario (such as debugging or code editing).  To manually add or remove toolbars:
1. Right-click in the toolbar area below the menu to see a list of available toolbars:

    ![Toolbars](toolbar-list.png "Toolbars")

1. Click any toolbar in the list to hide or show it.
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>

    <vst:Step Title="Next steps"
              Id="NextSteps"
              IsScreenshot="false">
        <vst:Step.Description>
            <![CDATA[
Congratulations on completing this Guide! We hope you enjoyed learning about personalizing Visual Studio.

**This is the end of the guide. Thank you for learning! [Please help us improve this Guide by sharing feedback here.](https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/DBNB57F?TutorialId=IdeCustomization)**

![Congratulations](congrats_tutorial.png "Congratulations")
]]>
        </vst:Step.Description>
    </vst:Step>

</vst:Guide>